## **Oliver Diamond**

diamond.oliver@gmail.com | 07846 394 258

I am a full-stack (mostly JS: React & Node) developer with a eclectic career. Experienced in approaches that emphasise small composable apps, devops, fast & frequent delivery, clean code, and developer anarchy.

- Current Position: Tes Software Engineer
- Specialisms: Node, React, Mongo, Microservices
- Passions: Linux, Functional, Devops, Spacemacs
- Physics, 2:1, Imperial College London (specialism: Computational Simulations)
- Extensive experience outside programming: Finance, Politics, Media, Communications

#### **Background**

I have been programming since I was 13 - building web MMORPGs with friends (*HTML & PHP*) with 1000s of players. At university (2:1 Physics) I spent 2 years programming a bio-ecosystem simulation (*C++*, *OO design*).

Not always a programmer though, I have worked in politics, film production, TV & theatre development, and finance. However, I pushed and built tech solutions in all of these industries from simple web apps (Node, Python, Ruby), to finance & news analysis apps (Java). I trained and then worked for a top dev bootcamp, focussing on professional full-stack skills and modern methodologies.

Currently I work for Tes (formerly the Times Education Supplement) and (most recently) for HSBC and Makers Academy. I've worked predominantly with the latest Javascript technologies, pushing the following philosphies: **devops, agile, microservices architectures, continuous delivery, constant retrospection and developer anarchy**, whilst always focussing on releasing value to clients.

#### Skills

#### **Programming:**

- JavaScript (Latest ES, Node, React, Express, Dojo, JQuery, RxJS, Selenium) 6+ yrs
- Clojure (Compojure) 1+ yrs
- Java (Android, Spring) 2+ yrs
- Ruby (Rails), Python (Django)
- C++
- CSS, SCSS
- DB (MySQL, PostgreSQL, Mongo)

#### Delivery/Ops:

- Microservices (Docker, RabbitMQ, Kubernetes, AWS)
- Continuous Delivery (Jenkins, TeamCity, Heroku)
- Version control: Git, RTC
- Linux (Redhat, Debian, Ubuntu)
- Networking (DNS, TCP/IP, HTTPS)
- Spacemacs (Emacs + Vim), Eclipse, Intelli|, Android Studio

#### Methodologies:

- Devops (Fast release cycles)
- Agile (lots of retrospecting)
- Test Driven Development
- Behaviour Driven Development
- Pair Programming
- Microservices Architectures

#### Other Expertise

**Government:** I have 8 years experience across Government, public policy, and the digital & creative industries. I became leader of a Minister's Parliamentary Office, and I continue to support a political network that I helped to found.

**Finance:** Aside from my tech work in HSBC's FX department, I have also worked in a credit-trading hedge fund, a Chinese event-driven brokerage, and a corporate finance boutique (analysing media and tech investments).

**Communications:** I have worked on public policy campaigns, in political communications, and in film & theatre marketing. I have written articles for national newspapers, press releases for a Minister of State, and organised political conferences.

#### **Work History**

#### **Tes Engineering (Oct 2017 - Present)** | *SOFTWARE ENGINEER*

An old company ( $\sim$ 100 years), Tes provide teaching resources and solutions. Now that online is the focus of the business, we have recently ungone a massive update to their engineering department.

We're now almost totally microservices, with a JS stack (React, Node, Mongo, funcational design), everything is Dockerised and runs on AWS.

We embrace continuous & fast delivery, agile, devops, open-source, developer anarchy, tiny teams (2-4), remote first, frequent retrospection, hackdays, and a focus on team building and the education of junior developers.

#### HSBC GFX (Dec 2016 - Sept 2017) | DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

My team of 6 delivered a suite of microservices in Clojure and ES6 and patched them into a legacy Java 6 / dojo.js monolith.

We worked from within the modernising, agile-embracing, daily-delivering, foriegn-exchange department of the investment bank, to bring their products into HSBCnet, one of the world's most used commercial payment applications, developed on a quarterly release cycle, with manual testing, and old SDLCs - straddling the politics of the 2 worlds.

#### Makers Academy (May 2016 - Sept 2017) | SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONSULTANT

I was involved from the beginning in Makers Academy's Consultancy arm. I had a remit to work on Makers' education-based platform (Ruby on Rails) when not with a corporate partner (HSBC, Tek Systems, & Allegis Group). True to the MA spirit, I also completed the Makers Academy course - a bootcamp focusing on professional programming best practices (Agile, TDD, BDD, Pair Programming and the philosphies of Sandi Metz, Robert C Martin & Fred George).

#### Bob & Co (Nov 2014 - May 2016) | HEAD OF DIGITAL AND COMMUNICATIONS

A small media (film, TV, theatre) developer, and financier. I ran the technological, research & communication efforts. I also built (and maintained) the company website (single-handed), and other applications (Java & JS) for their partners & subsidiaries.

I later became Acting Director of Operations during a staff maternity leave, tasked with extensive audit and efficiency efforts in the IT, telecoms, and other office admin budgets.

#### SUMS Film & Media (Aug 2015 - Dec 2015) | DIGITAL & TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT

An independent film producer. I directly advised the Cheif Executive on their projects' digital strategies (see IMDB  $\leftarrow$  I'm three clicks from Tom Cruise). I worked on various applications, including marketing websites (*PHP*).

#### North Square Blue Oak (Jan 2014 - Mar 2014) | SABBATICAL ANALYST

A brokerage and corporate finance boutique, assessing new corporate finance opportunities in the digital sectors. The company drew heavily on my technological expertise in assessing potential investments.

### **CQS Asset Management (Feb 2013 - Mar 2013)** | *MARGINS DEPT ANALYST & DEVELOPMENT INTERN*A \$13bn credit hedge fund: in liability management analysis with collateral specialists (creating an app to ass

A \$13bn credit hedge fund: in liability management analysis with collateral specialists (creating an app to assess marginal risks); and also with the strategic IT team, developing a credit price monitoring application (C#).

# Office of the Digital & Cultural Minister (Nov 2008 - Nov 2014) | SENIOR PARLIAMENTARY ADVISOR I managed the Parliamentary Office of Rt. Hon. Ed Vaizey MP from the date of his Ministerial appointment. I oversaw the running of the office, interviewing, training and managing all junior staff. I worked on campaigns such as improving Wifi provision in public libraries and bringing coding into the national curriculum.

Aside from working on digital & media policy, I was given a wide remit and free-reign within the office, so I often programmed solutions to office problems, developing wordpress applications (*PHP*) for websites and databasing needs, and MS Access applications for automating emails and training.

#### **Education**

#### Physics 2:1 (BSc & ARCS): Imperial College London (Oct 2005 - July 2008)

I focussed on computational simulations, astrophysics, plasma physics, and the practicalities of nuclear fusion energy as a future energy source.

#### Final Year Degree Project (C++)

I received 93% for an computer simulation investigation into the process of evolution. I wrote the program from scratch, modelling biological systems. I was praised particularly for analysing great amounts of data, spotting patterns and anomalies, presenting them accessibly and quantifying the results in a manner that the department had never seen before.

#### **Other Interests**

#### CACIN - The Political Creative Industries Network (2008 - 2017) | DIRECTOR

I developed and maintained relationships with many key players in the tech & creative sectors on behalf Damian Collins MP, the Rt Hon Minister Ed Vaizey MP, and the Conservative Party HQ. I ran regular panels, drinks receptions and conferences across the UK, focusing on issues from the digital single market to diversity in the media.

**The Digital Bazaar, Tate South Lambeth Library (2009 - 2013)** | FOUNDING VOLUNTEER & IT EXPERT Taught basic computer, smartphone and other technology use to struggling members of the Lambeth community (many of whom did not have English as a first language). Runners-up for the CILIP Libraries Change Lives Award 2012.

**Music** - I have an intensely musical education. A music scholarship took me through secondary school. I sang in Christ Church Cathedral Choir, Oxford (we sang the credits to Blackadder and Vicar of Dibley; we performed in front of HM the queen; and we toured the USA, Japan, Germany, France, and Brazil). I also played the Saxophone, Violin, Piano, and guitar.

**Cooking** - I love cooking and spend a great deal of time in the kitchen. I have been paid to cook at events. And my recipes are popular on Instagram.

Tennis - I play regularly with a variety of partners and am coached professionally.